<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: adobecreativecloud | Matthew Riley]]></title>
  <link href="http://matthewriley.us/categories/adobecreativecloud/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://matthewriley.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-17T10:53:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://matthewriley.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Riley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adobe Proto: Efficient Wireframing]]></title>
    <link href="http://matthewriley.us/adobe-proto-efficient-wireframing"/>
    <updated>2011-11-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://matthewriley.us/adobe-proto-efficient-wireframing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Adobe has launched a new cloud platform called Adobe Creative Cloud. Creative Cloud intends to extend the creative process to the cloud by enabling cloud access across all of Adobe's creative tools, collectively known as the Adobe Creative Suite. A significant aspect of this initiative is a set of tablet based apps. The Adobe Touch Apps family is made up of Photoshop Touch, Adobe Debut, Adobe Proto, Adobe Collage, Adobe Ideas and Adobe Kuler.</p>

<p>Adobe Proto allows you to create interactive wireframes for websites using a touch interface on a tablet. I've used a number of other desktop and web based wireframing and prototyping tools in the past but not a tablet based tool. When I saw the demo of Proto online from Adobe MAX, I was immediately interested. I've been using Proto for a few days now and I've had a positive experience with it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The workflow to create a wireframe in Proto is relatively straight forward. Once you start a new project, building your wireframe is as easy as drawing it on the screen. This is accomplished using a few predefined gestures. Each gesture corresponds to a form element or navigation widget. If you don't want to draw your screen elements, you have the option to manually select each item from a toolbar and place it on the screen.</p>

<p>Beyond wireframing, Proto also allows a basic level of interactivity. Once you have built your first wireframe, you can add a second page and link to it from the first. This is not very advanced functionality but if you're building an alpha grade wireframe, you don't need it to be. Once you have your wireframe built, Proto has a preview feature that allows you to view and interact with your design.</p>

<p>The power behind Creative Cloud is the ability to access and share your creations from multiple locations and the Adobe Touch apps, including Proto, have this built-in. You can upload your completed designs to Adobe's cloud. From the Creative Cloud website, you can share the design to others via email, preview the wireframe directly or download it to your desktop as a zip file. The zip file contains an html file for each page and a css file.</p>

<p>Usage of the Creative Cloud is highly recommended but not required to use Proto. I'd like to see an option to share the design via email directly from the app. Also, exporting the design to an image may be useful. At my day job, we currently share wireframes to our business users as images in a wiki page. I think it would also be very useful if I could import a project from the Creative Cloud in case I delete it from my device.</p>

<p>When working with Proto I found that the responsiveness felt like it was running at 80% - 90%. Fast, but not as fast and responsive as I'd like. Also, I think grid snapping could be improved. This applies not only to the grid but also relative center snapping and in line snapping to other objects.</p>

<p>I'm primarily a web applications developer and I found Proto to be geared more towards website developers. For example, the canvas that the grid in on is an infinite vertical scrolling grid. Web applications and mobile applications typically have a fixed viewport. I'd like to see an option to build a wireframe within fixed dimensions. Also, I need more widgets and UI elements such as grids, panels, tree navigation and far more form elements including input elements we see on mobile platforms.</p>

<p>I don't want to emphasize the pain points too much because they're minor in comparison to the potential wireframing productivity gains Proto offers. Other browser and desktop based packages currently available are, at times, cumbersome. It seems odd to create interface mock-ups in tools that themselves have less than optimal interfaces. Having a touch interface gives Proto a clear and distinct advantage over other tools. That advantage translates into a noticeable increase in efficiency when creating prototype designs.</p>

<p>Adobe Proto may not be a feature complete tool but it is certainly one of the most efficient, if not the most efficient wireframing tool out there. I was able to wireframe designs with Proto in less than half the time it took in other tools. When you're working to get alpha grade wireframe designs out the door and in front of your customers or business owners, Adobe Proto will go a long way in you helping out.</p>

<p>For more information on Adobe Proto visit:<br/>
<a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/proto.html">http://www.adobe.com/products/proto.html</a></p>

<p>For more information on Adobe Creative Cloud visit:<br/>
<a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/creativecloud.html">http://www.adobe.com/products/creativecloud.html</a></p>

<p>Below is a quick demo of Proto I created (admittedly poorly lit and low resolution) showing how fast wireframing with Proto is.</p>

<p><iframe width="" height="" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/zvHONVipDOA " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
